<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cortex – community</title><link>/tags/community/</link><description>Recent content in community on Cortex</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Blog: Introducing the Cortex Blog: Sharing Our Journey</title><link>/blog/2025/04/26/introducing-the-cortex-blog-sharing-our-journey/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2025/04/26/introducing-the-cortex-blog-sharing-our-journey/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Welcome to the official Cortex blog!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We’re kicking things off here to share updates, best practices,
technical deep-dives, and community highlights around everything Cortex.
Whether you&amp;rsquo;re operating a Cortex cluster, integrating it into your observability platform,
or just starting to explore scalable time-series databases — you&amp;rsquo;re in the right place.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the coming weeks, you can expect posts on:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Real-world Cortex deployment strategies and lessons learned&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tips for running Cortex efficiently at scale&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deep dives into key Cortex concepts like blocks storage, ruler sharding, and query federation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Guides to help new contributors get involved with the project&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Interviews with maintainers and users from across the community&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Roadmap insights and upcoming features we&amp;rsquo;re excited about&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Cortex has grown a lot thanks to a vibrant community of operators, contributors, and partners.
This blog will be another space for us to connect, learn from each other, and push the project even further.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stay tuned — the first technical post is coming soon!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If there&amp;rsquo;s a topic you’d love to see covered, feel free to reach out or open a discussion in our &lt;a href="https://github.com/cortexproject/cortex/discussions">Cortex community forums&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks for being part of the journey! 🚀&lt;/p>
&lt;p>— The Cortex Team&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>